<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vinicius Moraes</title>
    <link>https://eternodevir.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Vinicius Moraes</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 10:29:37 -0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://eternodevir.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Hello, w̶o̶r̶l̶d̶!</title>
      <link>https://eternodevir.com/home/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 19:16:33 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eternodevir.com/home/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;m Vinicius Moraes and this is my personal corner on the internet. Here you can follow my productions and read about the most varied topics.
Blog indexation:
Categories
Broadcasts — playlists, podcasts, videos and other non-text formats. Essays — texts that deepen themes of interest. Notes — notes, comments, interpretations. Topics
Autobiography — personal productions. Cinema — cinematic art and movies. Computer — programming, GNU Linux, Emacs, self-hosting. Reading — books, poems, short stories, articles.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Publications</title>
      <link>https://eternodevir.com/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 00:40:43 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eternodevir.com/publications/</guid>
      <description>Article Metamorfoses: a transformação dos mitos e o ato de (re)contar histórias. Rónai – Revista de Estudos Clássicos e Tradutórios, vol. 4, no. 2, 2016, pp. 71-78. Monograph O abismo do original: a bitradução simultânea de Malone Morre, de Samuel Beckett, por Paulo Leminski. Trabalho de Conclusão de Curso, UFJF, Juiz de Fora, 2021. Work Ekphrasis and Other Forms of Text-Image Relations: Open City by Teju Cole. Presentation, Universität Passau, Passau, 2018.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://eternodevir.com/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2023 15:34:29 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eternodevir.com/about/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;#39;m a Bachelor of Arts graduate from the Federal University of Juiz de Fora (UFJF), where I majored in Portuguese and Translation. For my undergraduate thesis, &amp;#34;The Abyss of the Original&amp;#34;, I addressed Leminski&amp;#39;s simultaneous bitranslation of Beckett&amp;#39;s &amp;#34;Malone Dies&amp;#34; and &amp;#34;Malone Meurt&amp;#34;. Within my academic program, I pursued topics in Classical Studies, Semiotics, Translation Theory, Computational Linguistics, and a range of other subjects.
But don&amp;#39;t let my fall for the Babel Tower fool you, when I&amp;#39;m not lost in the world of language, I&amp;#39;m probably diving deep in some other world—overall the worlds of cinema, philosophy, and technology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rendez-vous 1408</title>
      <link>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/10/rendez-vous-1408/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2020 11:01:24 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/10/rendez-vous-1408/</guid>
      <description>Songs that accompanied soirée nights, meetings with dear friends, and late-night pool dips during college days at 1408.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Psychopolitics</title>
      <link>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/06/psychopolitics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 10:52:51 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/06/psychopolitics/</guid>
      <description>Byung-Chul Han, as a writer and philosopher, has an admirable quality: he writes clearly and objectively about complex topics. Even so, it was a laborious book due to the constant need to separate the wheat from the chaff. However, once the cause of the problem was identified, the reading was quite fruitful. The work is divided into thirteen sections/essays: (1) crisis of freedom; (2) intelligent power; (3) the mole and the serpent; (4) biopolitics; (5) Foucault&amp;#39;s dilemma; (6) healing as murder; (7) shock; (8) the lovable big brother; (9) the capitalism of emotion; (10) gamification; (11) big data; (12) beyond the subject; and (13) idiocy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One-Dimensional Man</title>
      <link>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/06/one-dimensional-man/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 18:36:32 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/06/one-dimensional-man/</guid>
      <description>In a less commercial translation, “One-Dimensional Man: Studies in the Ideology of Developed Industrial Society”, published in 1964. A book with many strengths. Marcuse is a dialectical thinker par excellence. If, on the one hand, he demonstrates how technology modifies production instruments and promotes advances towards human emancipation, on the other hand, he assesses how technology is part of a new form of control, impacting: (i) work; (ii) the political universe; (iii) conscience; (iv) the locution universe; (v) culture; and (vi) thought.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I write to find out what I think</title>
      <link>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/05/i-write-to-find-out-what-i-think/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 00:02:29 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/05/i-write-to-find-out-what-i-think/</guid>
      <description>The other day, I remembered my high school math teacher and how combinatorics was one of the few topics I was interested in. Somehow, it seemed to delight me being able to envision a universe of possibilities within a given circumstance. This morning, I ended up putting that memory together with an idea that has been inhabiting me lately: that of writing as an exercise of reflection and discovery. Lessons that never end…</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Until the glorious end</title>
      <link>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/03/until-the-glorious-end/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2020 23:26:08 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/03/until-the-glorious-end/</guid>
      <description>Caixa Cultural, São Paulo, 2015 Essay by Paulo Leminski, published in 1989 in Folha de Londrina, months before his death.
Body not mind When Francis Xavier, the Jesuit missionary, landed in Japan, at the height of navigation, his catechesis produced thousands of conversions and Catholicism began to spread across the country.
In the letters he wrote to his superiors in Rome, Xavier describes with joy the progress of the apostolate in the Land of the Rising Sun.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Party of the bothered ones</title>
      <link>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/02/party-of-the-bothered-ones/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 00:57:28 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/02/party-of-the-bothered-ones/</guid>
      <description>A bothered person talks about some annoyance. Some bothered ones agree, other bothered ones disagree. At the party, those who aren&amp;#39;t bothered are divided into two groups of people who are bothered: those who aren&amp;#39;t bothered by that annoyance, but by the fact that there are so many bothered people bothering them; and those who aren&amp;#39;t bothered by absolutely nothing, with the exception of those who aren&amp;#39;t bothered by being bothered by so many bothers, which, it&amp;#39;s known, causes them a deep annoyance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>For Street Cinema memories</title>
      <link>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2019/02/for-street-cinema-memories/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Feb 2019 20:36:05 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2019/02/for-street-cinema-memories/</guid>
      <description>Cinearte Palace, Juiz de Fora, 2017 Glauber Rocha taught me to perceive, at the heart of Cinema Novo, the real possibility of a national cinema going beyond a purely commercial logic. Art, to some extent and with all the difficulties, still resisting as a stage for something uncertain, unexpected. A space of plural resistance, of the creative singularity of each director, of each film, where the obvious and the predetermined, of lucrative Hollywood formulas, refuse to happen.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
