<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>autobiography on Eterno Devir</title>
        <link>https://eternodevir.com/tags/autobiography/</link>
        <description>Recent content in autobiography on Eterno Devir</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <managingEditor>Vinicius Moraes &lt;vinicius.moraes@eternodevir.com&gt;</managingEditor>
        <webMaster>Vinicius Moraes &lt;vinicius.moraes@eternodevir.com&gt;</webMaster>
        <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 00:02:29 -0300</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://eternodevir.com/tags/autobiography/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>I write to find out what I think</title>
            <link>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/05/i-write-to-find-out-what-i-think/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 00:02:29 -0300</pubDate>
            <author><name>Vinicius Moraes</name>
	    <email>vinicius.moraes@eternodevir.com</email></author>
            <guid>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/05/i-write-to-find-out-what-i-think/</guid>
            <description>The other day, I remembered my high school math teacher and how combinatorics was one of the few topics I was interested in. Somehow, it seemed to delight me being able to envision an universe of possibilities within a given circumstance. This morning, I ended up putting that memory together with an idea that has been inhabiting me lately: that of writing as an exercise of reflection and discovery. Lessons that never end…</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<p>
<figure><img src="/images/escrevo-para-descobrir-o-que-penso/image1.jpg"/>
</figure>
</p>
<p>
The other day, I remembered my high school math teacher and how combinatorics was one of the few topics I was interested in. Somehow, it seemed to delight me being able to envision an universe of possibilities within a given circumstance. This morning, I ended up putting that memory together with an idea that has been inhabiting me lately: that of writing as an exercise of reflection and discovery. Lessons that never end…</p>
<div id="outline-container-headline-1" class="outline-4">
<h4 id="headline-1">
Combinatorial analysis exercise I
</h4>
<div id="outline-text-headline-1" class="outline-text-4">
<p>
I write to discover what I think.<br>
I think to write what I discover.<br>
I discover to think what I write.<br>
I write to think what I discover.<br>
I think to discover what I write.<br>
I discover to write what I think.</p>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Party of the bothered ones</title>
            <link>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/02/party-of-the-bothered-ones/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 00:57:28 -0300</pubDate>
            <author><name>Vinicius Moraes</name>
	    <email>vinicius.moraes@eternodevir.com</email></author>
            <guid>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/02/party-of-the-bothered-ones/</guid>
            <description>A bothered person talks about some annoyance. Some bothered ones agree, other bothered ones disagree. At the party, those who aren&amp;#39;t bothered are divided into two groups of people who are bothered: those who aren&amp;#39;t bothered by that annoyance, but by the fact that there are so many bothered people bothering them; and those who aren&amp;#39;t bothered by absolutely nothing, with the exception of those who aren&amp;#39;t bothered by being bothered by so many bothers, which, it&amp;#39;s known, causes them a deep annoyance.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
A bothered person talks about some annoyance. Some bothered ones agree, other bothered ones disagree. At the party, those who aren&#39;t bothered are divided into two groups of people who are bothered: those who aren&#39;t bothered by that annoyance, but by the fact that there are so many bothered people bothering them; and those who aren&#39;t bothered by absolutely nothing, with the exception of those who aren&#39;t bothered by being bothered by so many bothers, which, it&#39;s known, causes them a deep annoyance.</p>
<p>
In the end, the only ones who decided not to go to the party weren&#39;t bothered – which certainly bothered a lot of people. I mean, that&#39;s how it seemed… at least until they realized they weren&#39;t even invited.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
