<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>autobiography on Vinicius Moraes</title>
    <link>https://eternodevir.com/tags/autobiography/</link>
    <description>Recent content in autobiography on Vinicius Moraes</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 00:02:29 -0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://eternodevir.com/tags/autobiography/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>I write to find out what I think</title>
      <link>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/05/i-write-to-find-out-what-i-think/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 00:02:29 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/05/i-write-to-find-out-what-i-think/</guid>
      <description>The other day, I remembered my high school math teacher and how combinatorics was one of the few topics I was interested in. Somehow, it seemed to delight me being able to envision a universe of possibilities within a given circumstance. This morning, I ended up putting that memory together with an idea that has been inhabiting me lately: that of writing as an exercise of reflection and discovery. Lessons that never end…</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Party of the bothered ones</title>
      <link>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/02/party-of-the-bothered-ones/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 00:57:28 -0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/02/party-of-the-bothered-ones/</guid>
      <description>A bothered person talks about some annoyance. Some bothered ones agree, other bothered ones disagree. At the party, those who aren&amp;#39;t bothered are divided into two groups of people who are bothered: those who aren&amp;#39;t bothered by that annoyance, but by the fact that there are so many bothered people bothering them; and those who aren&amp;#39;t bothered by absolutely nothing, with the exception of those who aren&amp;#39;t bothered by being bothered by so many bothers, which, it&amp;#39;s known, causes them a deep annoyance.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
