<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Blog on Eterno Devir</title>
        <link>https://eternodevir.com/blog/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Blog on Eterno Devir</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <managingEditor>Vinicius Moraes &lt;vinicius.moraes@eternodevir.com&gt;</managingEditor>
        <webMaster>Vinicius Moraes &lt;vinicius.moraes@eternodevir.com&gt;</webMaster>
        <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 10:29:37 -0300</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://eternodevir.com/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Rendez-vous 1408</title>
            <link>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/10/rendez-vous-1408/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2020 11:01:24 -0300</pubDate>
            <author><name>Vinicius Moraes</name>
	    <email>vinicius.moraes@eternodevir.com</email></author>
            <guid>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/10/rendez-vous-1408/</guid>
            <description>Songs that accompanied soirée nights, meetings with dear friends, and late-night pool dips during college days at 1408.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Songs that accompanied soirée nights, meetings with dear friends, and late-night pool dips during college days at 1408.</p>
<p>
 
 <div style="margin: 25px 0px">
 
 <iframe src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/playlist/5yZp29Dlx1ftTTsqPwH9uy"
     width="100%"
     height="480"
     frameborder="0"
     allowtransparency="true"
     allow="encrypted-media"></iframe>
 
 </div>
</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Psychopolitics</title>
            <link>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/06/psychopolitics/</link>
            <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 10:52:51 -0300</pubDate>
            <author><name>Vinicius Moraes</name>
	    <email>vinicius.moraes@eternodevir.com</email></author>
            <guid>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/06/psychopolitics/</guid>
            <description>Byung-Chul Han, as a writer and philosopher, has an admirable quality: he writes clearly and objectively about complex topics. Even so, it was a laborious book due to the constant need to separate the wheat from the chaff. However, once the cause of the problem was identified, the reading was quite fruitful. The work is divided into thirteen sections/essays: (1) crisis of freedom; (2) intelligent power; (3) the mole and the serpent; (4) biopolitics; (5) Foucault&amp;#39;s dilemma; (6) healing as murder; (7) shock; (8) the lovable big brother; (9) the capitalism of emotion; (10) gamification; (11) big data; (12) beyond the subject; and (13) idiocy.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
Byung-Chul Han, as a writer and philosopher, has an admirable quality: he writes clearly and objectively about complex topics. Even so, it was a laborious book due to the constant need to separate the wheat from the chaff. However, once the cause of the problem was identified, the reading was quite fruitful. The work is divided into thirteen sections/essays: (1) crisis of freedom; (2) intelligent power; (3) the mole and the serpent; (4) biopolitics; (5) Foucault&#39;s dilemma; (6) healing as murder; (7) shock; (8) the lovable big brother; (9) the capitalism of emotion; (10) gamification; (11) big data; (12) beyond the subject; and (13) idiocy.</p>
<p>
In summary, in the development of some theses, Byung-Chul argues that neoliberalism operates the transition: from the biopolitical society (body control) to the psychopolitical society (mind control); from disciplinary power (negative and violent) to intelligent power (positive and internalized); from productivity by exploring rationality to productivity by exploring emotion (gamification of work and life, reward system); from the worker-subject (classist, proletarian) to the project-subject (self-entrepreneur); from the exploitation of man by man (exploiter and exploited) to the exploitation of man by himself (“self-exploitation”); from the material mode of production (material objects) to the immaterial mode of production (“emotion/like capitalism”, sociability and communication are exploited); from human memory (forgetting and narrative) to digital memory (non-forgetting and quantification); from the repressive forces against expression (censorship) to the seductive forces of expression (social networks); from extrinsic surveillance (secret services) to intrinsic surveillance (self-exposure); from Bentham&#39;s panopticon (prison and isolation, optical control) to the digital panopticon (illusory freedom and communication, big data).</p>
<p>
The chaff is that, in several of the theses presented, Byung-Chul does not operate in terms of a dialectical relationship between the elements, or even of deepening, but rather in terms of complete transformation. Therefore, in the first 11 sections, neoliberalism assumes an absolute and deterministic disposition, generating some conclusions detached from reality even if based on half-truths. In my reading, the root of this problem comes from the realization that neoliberalism “eliminated the extrinsic exploitation of the working class”, so that there would be no proletariat (a class exploited by another) in neoliberalism. Now, one thing is verifying that neoliberalism new techniques of power operate in the sense of omitting (!) antagonism and class struggle, “internalizing exploitation” in workers and affecting individuals “at a pre-reflective level”. Another thing is taking it as an absolute/deterministic aspect of reality. That is, Byung-Chul completely erases the existence of class struggle within neoliberal society, which leads him to revise Marx (by the way, others as well, including Foucault). For Byung-Chul, neoliberalism transforms workers into entrepreneurs of themselves through “self-exploitation” (half-truth) to the point where the class antagonism between exploited and exploiters has been eliminated (false).</p>
<p>
To elucidate the problem with just one concrete example: Byung-Chul describes the gamification of work (reward system, productivity by exploring emotion, etc.) and “self-exploration” (self-entrepreneur) of neoliberal logic, that is, observable aspects in the reality of couriers using apps (point system, absence of employment relantionship, etc.); however, there is no scope in the proposed theory to contemplate the classist and concrete organization of couriers in the fight against (self)exploitation, claiming better working conditions and explaining in all letters: “nobody here is an entrepreneur, we are a workforce” . In other words, the practice of those who fight in a classist and antagonistic way against the exploitation imposed by capital in favor of the bourgeoisie, the dominant class for holding ownership of the means of production (it is important to remember), puts Byung-Chul&#39;s revisionist defeatism in check . That said, with regard to the exploitation of labor in neoliberalism, a complementary synthesis/epigraph would be: “protect me from what I need to do to survive”; however much, in relation to the alleged digital freedom and big data, the epigraph of the work remains relevant: “protect me from what I want” (Jenny Holzer).</p>
<p>
Disagreements aside, in addition to the gamification of life and work, I emphasize the passages about the quantified self and the applications of big data, via artificial intelligence, as a form of neoliberal domination in the most varied spheres of life. The imperative in the digital age is for everything to become data and information, in such a way that, through the quantified self (followers, likes, number of friends) and big data, <em>digitus</em> begins to take the place of <em>phallus</em>. In this sense, human sociability and communication, under the pretext of an illusory freedom of neoliberalism, play a central role in the production of masses of data and information. In view of this, mining via artificial intelligence of this immense amount of data that we produce daily is capable of creating a faithful “digital/multidimensional version of ourselves”, influencing and predicting our behavior and even accessing our most intimate thoughts and desires. In this context, even our unconscious is exploited, both individual and collective. That is, through big data and artificial intelligence, neoliberalism managed to merge exploitation, commercialization, information, surveillance and domination (the junction between Big Brother, Big Data and Big Business, in Byung-Chul&#39;s terms). A concrete example is the influence of big data from a private company on the course of the 2016 US elections. Notwithstanding, by way of mention, Byung-Chul provides one of the best metaphorical explanations of data mining and big data. He makes an allusion between Dataism and Dadaism, which later unfolds into a metaphor to reflect on the power and implications artificial intelligence black blox (although he does not address this concept directly in the book).</p>
<p>
Finally, in the last two sections, Byung-Chul suspends the deterministic disposition of his analysis of neoliberalism and proposes a philosophical way out to combat it: idiocy. Explaining in a reductionist way, being an idiot in the Socratic sense of the posture of knowing that you know nothing. For Byung-Chul, intelligence means “choosing-between” within the logic of a system. Thus, intelligence would not be entirely free for having to choose according to what the system offers. Idiotism, on the other hand, would be completely free because it is heretical and alien (“outsider”) to the systemic immanence of intelligence. The idiot, through the immanence of emptiness, remains silent and in solitude and, therefore, finds the singularity of what is “really worth saying” (in a negative sense [“subversive”] in relation to the system). The idiot, therefore, would not exist as a subject of the system (contrasting the individualism of neoliberalism), he would be more like “a flower: an existence simply open to the light”, being characterized not by individuality, but by singularity. Despite not being directly explained, the idiot somewhat resembles Zarathustra or a Buddhist monk, which makes sense in view of the theoretical references of this philosophical departure proposed by Byung-Chul: Nietzsche, Deleuze, Clément Rosset and Botho Strauss.</p>
<p>
In conclusion, it is a relevant book for understanding the new techniques of power and exploitation of neoliberalism, but which, in my view, does not incisively contribute to overcoming this domination, to the radical transformation of this reality, given the defeatism of Byung- Chul before the famous maxim of thesis eleven. As much as there are interesting reflections from a strictly philosophical point of view, I don&#39;t know of any oppressed people who have effectively fought their exploitation, as proposed by idiocy. The same, however, cannot be said about the much criticized Marxist praxis. The struggle organized in a classist way was historically more effective towards the appreciation of life and human emancipation.</p>
<p>
Footnote for audiovisual lovers: there is not a single episode of Black Mirror that is not contemplated by some part of this book. The raw reality of all of us who are exploited, even digitally and psychologically, by capital. Some excerpts:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The capitalism of Like should come with a warning label: Protect me from what I want.  (pg. 16)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Under neoliberalism, the technology of power takes on a subtle form. It does not lay hold of individuals directly. Instead, it ensures that individuals act on themselves so that power relations are interiorized – and then interpreted as freedom. Self-optimization and submission, freedom and exploitation, fall into one.  (pg. 23)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The neoliberal regime is in the course of inaugurating the age of exhaustion. Today, the psyche itself is being exploited.  (pg. 24)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Neoliberal psychopolitics is dominated by positivity. Instead of working with negative threats, it works with positive stimuli. Instead of administering ‘bitter medicine’, it enlists Liking.  (pg. 28)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Today’s society of information is not characterized by destroying words, but by multiplying them without end.  (pg. 29)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>In the digital panopticon, the illusion of limitless freedom and communication predominates. Here there is no torture – just tweets and posts. Nor is there a mysterious ‘Ministry of Truth’. Transparency and information have taken the place of truth. The new conception of power does not involve controlling the past, but steering the future psychopolitically.  (pg. 30)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>The gamification of work exploits homo ludens. The player subjugates him- or herself to the order of domination in the very act of playing. Today, the gamification logic of ‘Likes’, ‘Friends’ and ‘Followers’ means that social communication is also being plugged into and subordinated to a game mode. The corollary of the gamification of communication is its commercialization. That said, this process is destroying human communication.  (pg. 38)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Belief that life admits measurement and quantification governs the digital age as a whole. ‘Quantified Self’ honours this faith too. The body is outfitted with sensors that automatically register data.  (pg. 45)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Who am I? ‘Quantified Self’ represents a Dadaist technology too; it empties the self of any and all meaning. The self gets broken down into data until no sense remains. (…) The motto of Quantified Self is ‘Self Knowledge through Numbers’. (pg. 46)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Big Data never forgets anything at all. For this reason alone, the digital panopticon is much more efficient than Bentham’s.  (pg. 47)</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>For instance, at a given stage of pregnancy, a woman may crave a particular product – yet this impulse marks a correlation of which she remains unaware. She buys the item, but she doesn’t know why. That’s how it is. Conceivably, this that’s-how-it-is (Es-ist-so) exists in psychic proximity to the Freudian id (Es), which escapes the ego and consciousness. In this light, Big Data is making the id into an ego to be exploited psychopolitically. If Big Data has access to the realm of our unconscious actions and inclinations, it is possible to construct a psychopolitics that would reach deep into our psyche to exploit it.  (pg. 48)</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>One-Dimensional Man</title>
            <link>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/06/one-dimensional-man/</link>
            <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 18:36:32 -0300</pubDate>
            <author><name>Vinicius Moraes</name>
	    <email>vinicius.moraes@eternodevir.com</email></author>
            <guid>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/06/one-dimensional-man/</guid>
            <description>In a less commercial translation, “One-Dimensional Man: Studies in the Ideology of Developed Industrial Society”, published in 1964. A book with many strengths. Marcuse is a dialectical thinker par excellence. If, on the one hand, he demonstrates how technology modifies production instruments and promotes advances towards human emancipation, on the other hand, he assesses how technology is part of a new form of control, impacting: (i) work; (ii) the political universe; (iii) conscience; (iv) the locution universe; (v) culture; and (vi) thought.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
In a less commercial translation, “One-Dimensional Man: Studies in the Ideology of Developed Industrial Society”, published in 1964. A book with many strengths. Marcuse is a dialectical thinker par excellence. If, on the one hand, he demonstrates how technology modifies production instruments and promotes advances towards human emancipation, on the other hand, he assesses how technology is part of a new form of control, impacting: (i) work; (ii) the political universe; (iii) conscience; (iv) the locution universe; (v) culture; and (vi) thought.</p>
<p>
In this sense, in short, this new form of control is the one-dimensional society and one-dimensional thinking. It is the ideology of developed industrial society – which is in one of its forms the “Welfare State”. In other words, a society and a thought that reaffirm themselves in the most varied spheres (particularities) in a positive way, rationalizing the irrational and harmonizing/suppressing negative (subversive) thinking, thus removing the (concrete) potentiality of other alternative forms of society (of transformation of the real).</p>
<p>
Overall, I found two aspects especially interesting. The first is that Marcuse does not fail to reaffirm that the social mode of production, and not technique, is the basic historical factor. The second is that the technological dilemma is not about a simple denial or affirmation in abstract, a technology can serve, at the same time, a capitalist or socialist society; however (!), this does not imply that technological and scientific transformations are not materializations of the values ​​of a given society. That is, the values ​​of a technology are not mere complements or external to it, but the technology itself is the materialization of these values. Scientific knowledge ditto.</p>
<p>
Finally, an account of the importance of dialectical thinking that permeates the book. The other day I was following a discussion on the internet in which both sides were right and wrong at the same time. Right because they pointed out real specificities about what they were discussing. Wrong because they denied the specificities pointed out to each other because, apparently, they were exclusive. That is, by denying the contradiction of what the other said, they lost sight of the more complex totality. Thus, they left a part of reality behind, misunderstood. They then fell into a kind of endless discursive battle. Anyway, despite being counter-intuitive (after all, the capitalist society structurally conditions us to have a one-dimensional thinking), it is perfectly possible to think of reality through the contradictory. And, although there are several, perhaps this is the greatest lesson that can be taken from the work: the refusal of unidimensional thinking and the practice of dialectical thinking. A feat that Marcuse performs with method and mastery throughout the book.</p>
<p>
By the way, the last page is synthetically exceptional:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>However, underneath the popular conservative base is the substratum of the outcasts and outsiders, the exploited and persecuted of other races and other colors, the unemployed and the unemployable. They exist outside the democratic process; its existence is the most immediate and real necessity of putting an end to intolerable conditions and institutions. Thus, their opposition is revolutionary even if their conscience is not. Its opposition reaches the system from the outside in, and therefore is not deflected by the system, it is an elemental force that violates the rules of the game and, in doing so, reveals the game as a cheated game. When they get together and take to the streets, without weapons, without protection, to claim the most primitive civil rights, they know that they are facing dogs, stones and bombs, jail, concentration camps and even death. Its strength is behind every political demonstration for victims of law and order. The fact that they begin to refuse to play the game may be the event that marks the beginning of the end of a period.</p>
<p>
Nothing indicates that it will be a good ending. The economic and technical capabilities of established societies are vast enough to allow adjustments and concessions to subdogs, and their armed forces sufficiently trained and equipped to handle emergency situations. Yet there is the spectrum again, within and beyond the borders of advanced societies. The easy historical parallel with barbarians threatening the empire of civilization prejudges the case; the second period of barbarism may well be the continued empire of civilization itself. But the probability is that, in that period, historical extremes may again meet: humanity&#39;s most advanced consciousness and its most exploited strength. It is nothing more than a probability. The critical theory of society has no concept that can bridge the gap between the present and its future; offering no promise and boasting no success, it remains negative. Thus, it wishes to remain loyal to those who, without hope, gave and give their lives to the Great Refusal.</p>
<p>
At the beginning of the Fascist era, Walter Benjamin wrote:</p>
<p>
Nur um der Hoffnungslosen willen ist uns die Hoffnung gegeben.</p>
<p>
Only on behalf of the hopeless are we given hope.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>I write to find out what I think</title>
            <link>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/05/i-write-to-find-out-what-i-think/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 May 2020 00:02:29 -0300</pubDate>
            <author><name>Vinicius Moraes</name>
	    <email>vinicius.moraes@eternodevir.com</email></author>
            <guid>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/05/i-write-to-find-out-what-i-think/</guid>
            <description>The other day, I remembered my high school math teacher and how combinatorics was one of the few topics I was interested in. Somehow, it seemed to delight me being able to envision a universe of possibilities within a given circumstance. This morning, I ended up putting that memory together with an idea that has been inhabiting me lately: that of writing as an exercise of reflection and discovery. Lessons that never end…</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<p>
<figure><img src="/images/escrevo-para-descobrir-o-que-penso/image1.jpg"/>
</figure>
</p>
<p>
The other day, I remembered my high school math teacher and how combinatorics was one of the few topics I was interested in. Somehow, it seemed to delight me being able to envision a universe of possibilities within a given circumstance. This morning, I ended up putting that memory together with an idea that has been inhabiting me lately: that of writing as an exercise of reflection and discovery. Lessons that never end…</p>
<div id="outline-container-headline-1" class="outline-4">
<h4 id="headline-1">
Combinatorial analysis exercise I
</h4>
<div id="outline-text-headline-1" class="outline-text-4">
<p>
I write to discover what I think.<br>
I think to write what I discover.<br>
I discover to think what I write.<br>
I write to think what I discover.<br>
I think to discover what I write.<br>
I discover to write what I think.</p>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Until the glorious end</title>
            <link>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/03/until-the-glorious-end/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 19 Mar 2020 23:26:08 -0300</pubDate>
            <author><name>Vinicius Moraes</name>
	    <email>vinicius.moraes@eternodevir.com</email></author>
            <guid>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/03/until-the-glorious-end/</guid>
            <description>Caixa Cultural, São Paulo, 2015 Essay by Paulo Leminski, published in 1989 in Folha de Londrina, months before his death.
Body not mind When Francis Xavier, the Jesuit missionary, landed in Japan, at the height of navigation, his catechesis produced thousands of conversions and Catholicism began to spread across the country.
In the letters he wrote to his superiors in Rome, Xavier describes with joy the progress of the apostolate in the Land of the Rising Sun.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[
<p>
<figure >
    
        <img src="/images/ate-o-glorioso-fim/image1.jpg"  />
    
    
    <figcaption>
        <h5>Caixa Cultural, São Paulo, 2015</h5>
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>
</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Essay by Paulo Leminski, published in 1989 in Folha de Londrina, months before his death.</p>
</blockquote>
<div id="outline-container-headline-1" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="headline-1">
Body not mind
</h2>
<div id="outline-text-headline-1" class="outline-text-2">
<p>
When Francis Xavier, the Jesuit missionary, landed in Japan, at the height of navigation, his catechesis produced thousands of conversions and Catholicism began to spread across the country.</p>
<p>
In the letters he wrote to his superiors in Rome, Xavier describes with joy the progress of the apostolate in the Land of the Rising Sun. In the same letters, however, he complains against the adherents of a sect called Zen (it must be the first mention of Zen in Europe). I can&#39;t convert any of that sect&#39;s adherents, Xavier confesses. They show no respect for sacred things, they laugh at everything and make fun of the symbols of our religion, he continues.</p>
<p>
The secret reason for Xavier&#39;s failure with Zen practitioners lies in the radical difference between body/mind (or body/soul) relationships in Catholicism and Zen. All Zen practices (Zen is – above all – a practice) aim to reach the body/mind fusion point, that alpha place where this distinction (seen as error and illusion) is no longer possible. They would aim, in a way, at a spiritualization of the body and an embodiment of the mind and spirit.</p>
<p>
This is very visible in martial arts, judo, kendo, karate, aikido, all soaked in zen. Those who practice martial arts soon learn that the body is not a machine governed by a brilliant commander called the mind. When applying a blow, it is clearly felt that the body is thinking. It is impossible not to see the parallels between this experience and the experience of sex which, to be fully realized, requires a moment of total fusion between a body that feels and a mind that directs. You can&#39;t get an erection or an orgasm thinking about tax reform…</p>
<p>
When trying to convert superiors of the Zen sect, with the basic phrase “save your soul”, Xavier ran into an insurmountable obstacle: the Zen monks could not conceive that the soul was something that people possessed and could have a different destiny from the body, its adventures, miseries and splendours. The art of a judoka or a karateka is not “una cosa mentale”, as Leonardo said of painting. It is essentially unitary, before or after the body/mind dichotomy that surreptitiously pervades all Western thought from Descartes onwards.</p>
<p>
The origins of this divorce from the indissociable are, of course, religious in nature: the mind of Western rationalism is the lay child of the salvageable soul of Christianity. No right to beyond the grave, however. But don&#39;t think that something so serious had only philosophical roots in the mind of some isolated thinker. The urban-industrial society, through the work methods it imposed, promotes the body/mind dissociation more than any metaphysical treatise.</p>
<p>
It is a disintegrating, detribalizing, atomizing force. There is no place for the body in the big factory, except as a work unit, never as a place of pleasure and sensory satisfaction. And the soul takes on the new names of “professional qualification”, “specialized training”, abstractions within that immense abstraction that is the anonymous industrial-urban society.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-headline-2" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="headline-2">
I command, you obey
</h2>
<div id="outline-text-headline-2" class="outline-text-2">
<p>
Slaves and masters. Nobles and servants. Bosses and employees. Technicians and workers. Nothing distinguishes man from animals more than the division of labor, our great strength and also the source of our weaknesses.</p>
<p>
It was through the division of labor that man multiplied his powers over nature at a fantastic speed: just 30,000 years ago all we had to face the hostility of the environment were weapons made of wood, stone and bone and clothing made from animal skins. In this biologically short period of time, we jumped from the wooden spear to the computer, electricity, genetic engineering and nuclear energy. This was only possible because man, in all latitudes, specialized certain groups of society in specific tasks. Any tiger knows how to do everything any tiger can do, and nothing more. Every tiger is a whole. We are fragmented. Some plant, others sell. Some command, others obey. Some celebrate ceremonies to the gods, others carry stones to build pyramids, temples and cathedrals.</p>
<p>
Who doesn&#39;t see that the mind/body dichotomy is a projection and a consequence of the division of labor, the division internalized in us? The mind is a metaphor for the ruling class served by the body.</p>
<p>
The division of labor is the true Original Sin, the one that expels us from paradise and launches us into the great adventure of life and the world. The serpent suggests, Eve picks the forbidden fruit, Adam eats it… To integrate mind and body is to return to the paradise that we can only experience in privileged moments: for disintegrated people, paradise is also experienced in the form of a fragment.</p>
<p>
One of the most radical moments in the division of labor is the separation between manual and intellectual work. This division begins in the religious world. Priests and farmers, monks and warriors, priests and faithful, are the remote model of the current division between technicians and theorists in the face of labor.</p>
<p>
And certain religious practices such as fasting, chastity, silence and the pursuit of physical discomfort have powerfully contributed to accelerating the split between body and mind. It would not be an exaggeration to imagine that the notion of the “soul” was born from these practices where the body is treated as an enemy, a beast that must be tamed, humiliated and reduced to being a docile mount under the reins of the “Spirit”.</p>
<p>
In the last century, when today&#39;s industrial rule begins, the figure of the “intellectual” appears, the man/mind par excellence, living only in the rarefied atmosphere of the “world of ideas”. With the intellectual, his affines, the technician, the specialist, the thinker…</p>
<p>
Between a body and a mind, a thousand light years of emptiness where monsters and demons, goblins and neuroses are created. The demons were called Lucifer, Beelzebub, Asmodeus, Belial. Today they are called neurosis, paranoia, schizophrenia, mania, anxiety. It is dangerous to separate what is by nature one and whole.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="outline-container-headline-3" class="outline-2">
<h2 id="headline-3">
Back to the unit
</h2>
<div id="outline-text-headline-3" class="outline-text-2">
<p>
Return to lost paradise, the reunion of mind and body cannot even be dreamed of, in full terms. That strange entity that is the human being, that we are, is irremediably split.</p>
<p>
The very exercise of what is called “reason” seems to be linked, flesh and nail, with the dissociation between a half that “thinks” and a body that obeys. We are condemned to reason. But it is this same dissociative ratio that can bring us closer, for enlightened moments, to the lost unity, at some light-year point in space/time.</p>
<p>
We seek this unity in the ludic and erotic practices, in art, sports, love and sex. In these areas of the in-utensil, life beyond the tyranny of profit and utility. By enjoyment and playing, we are safe, free. And back.</p>
<p>
For Zen, the secret is in everyday life itself. It is necessary to rescue the infinite grandeur of simple and “elementary” gestures. Take care of life. Enjoy the minutiae. Do your own laundry. The dishes. Tidy up the house. Make your food. Bathing like someone performing a sacred act. Recover the pleasure of the practice of primary acts. Knowing that being matter, cock and pussy, mouth and stomach, is a dignity and a splendor.</p>
<p>
It takes work.</p>
<p>
But to shine, the stars must burn, until the glorious end.</p>
<div id="outline-container-headline-4" class="outline-4">
<h4 id="headline-4">
Towards the lushness
</h4>
<div id="outline-text-headline-4" class="outline-text-4">
<p>
Disguise, there are people looking.<br>
Some look up,<br>
comets, moons, galaxies.<br>
Others look sideways,<br>
spyglasses, moonlights, syntaxes.<br>
Forward or aside,<br>
there are always people looking,<br>
looking or being looked at.</p>
<p>
Others look down,<br>
looking for some trace <br>
of the time we find,<br>
in search of lost time.<br>
Few look inside,<br>
since there&#39;s nothing inside.<br>
Just an immense weight,<br>
the soul, this fairy tale.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Party of the bothered ones</title>
            <link>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/02/party-of-the-bothered-ones/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 00:57:28 -0300</pubDate>
            <author><name>Vinicius Moraes</name>
	    <email>vinicius.moraes@eternodevir.com</email></author>
            <guid>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2020/02/party-of-the-bothered-ones/</guid>
            <description>A bothered person talks about some annoyance. Some bothered ones agree, other bothered ones disagree. At the party, those who aren&amp;#39;t bothered are divided into two groups of people who are bothered: those who aren&amp;#39;t bothered by that annoyance, but by the fact that there are so many bothered people bothering them; and those who aren&amp;#39;t bothered by absolutely nothing, with the exception of those who aren&amp;#39;t bothered by being bothered by so many bothers, which, it&amp;#39;s known, causes them a deep annoyance.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
A bothered person talks about some annoyance. Some bothered ones agree, other bothered ones disagree. At the party, those who aren&#39;t bothered are divided into two groups of people who are bothered: those who aren&#39;t bothered by that annoyance, but by the fact that there are so many bothered people bothering them; and those who aren&#39;t bothered by absolutely nothing, with the exception of those who aren&#39;t bothered by being bothered by so many bothers, which, it&#39;s known, causes them a deep annoyance.</p>
<p>
In the end, the only ones who decided not to go to the party weren&#39;t bothered – which certainly bothered a lot of people. I mean, that&#39;s how it seemed… at least until they realized they weren&#39;t even invited.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>For Street Cinema memories</title>
            <link>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2019/02/for-street-cinema-memories/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 03 Feb 2019 20:36:05 -0300</pubDate>
            <author><name>Vinicius Moraes</name>
	    <email>vinicius.moraes@eternodevir.com</email></author>
            <guid>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2019/02/for-street-cinema-memories/</guid>
            <description>Cinearte Palace, Juiz de Fora, 2017 Glauber Rocha taught me to perceive, at the heart of Cinema Novo, the real possibility of a national cinema going beyond a purely commercial logic. Art, to some extent and with all the difficulties, still resisting as a stage for something uncertain, unexpected. A space of plural resistance, of the creative singularity of each director, of each film, where the obvious and the predetermined, of lucrative Hollywood formulas, refuse to happen.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
<figure >
    
        <img src="/images/por-memorias-de-cinema-de-rua/image1.jpg"  />
    
    
    <figcaption>
        <h5>Cinearte Palace, Juiz de Fora, 2017</h5>
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>
</p>
<p>
Glauber Rocha taught me to perceive, at the heart of Cinema Novo, the real possibility of a national cinema going beyond a purely commercial logic. Art, to some extent and with all the difficulties, still resisting as a stage for something uncertain, unexpected. A space of plural resistance, of the creative singularity of each director, of each film, where the obvious and the predetermined, of lucrative Hollywood formulas, refuse to happen. Glauber put on stage the most genuine desire to practice what is instigating: experimentation, transformation, freedom.</p>
<p>
Little by little, it became increasingly difficult to find expressions of similar will, even more so with the growing dominance of major US productions in Brazil. The very space for experiencing the cinema was being transformed, shifted to large shopping centers. From the popularization and socialization of street cinemas to the mere commercial reduction and elitization of the public, with an increase in ticket prices and the experience of going to the cinema as a whole. Popular festivals and local productions were put in the background by the protagonism and profitability of blockbusters. The popcorn carts on the street removed from the scene by the exorbitant prices of food courts in malls… Surprisingly, despite seeming almost extinct, some spaces for meeting the unknown still resist.</p>
<p>
<figure >
    
        <img src="/images/por-memorias-de-cinema-de-rua/image2.jpg"  />
    
    
    <figcaption>
        <h5>Cine Roxy, Rio de Janeiro, 2018</h5>
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>
</p>
<p>
In the search for one of these places in Passau, I had the joy of finding the unexpected. In this small town on the border between Germany and Austria, 10,000 kilometers away from Brazil, a street cinema was showing the Brazilian feature &#34;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GxCOCthjc7o">Corpo Elétrico</a>&#34;, by Marcelo Caetano. Film that I was lucky and pleased to watch during one of the only two sessions that took place in Juiz de Fora. A film that reminds me of Glauber&#39;s genuine will, which, more than understanding, dares to invite us to feel. Corpo Elétrico made me reaffirm there, in the darkness of the emptied rows of that German street cinema, how surprising and fascinating these spaces are that, with a lot of effort, still encourage what is instigating and diverse. After having lived for seven years near the last street cinema in Juiz de Fora, I have never felt so close to home even so far away.</p>
<p>
<figure >
    
        <img src="/images/por-memorias-de-cinema-de-rua/image3.jpg"  />
    
    
    <figcaption>
        <h5>Metropolis, Passau, 2019</h5>
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>
</p>
<p>
<figure >
    
        <img src="/images/por-memorias-de-cinema-de-rua/image4.jpg"  />
    
    
    <figcaption>
        <h5>ProLi, Passau, 2019</h5>
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>
</p>
<p>
<figure >
    
        <img src="/images/por-memorias-de-cinema-de-rua/image5.jpg"  />
    
    
    <figcaption>
        <h5>Regina, Regensburg, 2019</h5>
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>
</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>The Seventh</title>
            <link>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2018/12/the-seventh/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2018 22:07:49 -0300</pubDate>
            <author><name>Vinicius Moraes</name>
	    <email>vinicius.moraes@eternodevir.com</email></author>
            <guid>https://eternodevir.com/blog/2018/12/the-seventh/</guid>
            <description>Cinearte Palace, Juiz de Fora, 2016 For some time now, it has become a habit to revisit films through the soundtrack. Reflecting on the subject, I realized that many of my cinematic memories are connected to the strength of this audiovisual relationship, especially some scenes closely linked to songs. The playlist below arose from the desire to remember and gather these memories.
Far from being just a background, songs are an integral part of the narrative itself when used well.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
<figure >
    
        <img src="/images/a-setima/image1.jpg"  />
    
    
    <figcaption>
        <h5>Cinearte Palace, Juiz de Fora, 2016</h5>
        
    </figcaption>
    
</figure>
</p>
<p>
For some time now, it has become a habit to revisit films through the soundtrack. Reflecting on the subject, I realized that many of my cinematic memories are connected to the strength of this audiovisual relationship, especially some scenes closely linked to songs. The playlist below arose from the desire to remember and gather these memories.</p>
<p>
Far from being just a background, songs are an integral part of the narrative itself when used well. Conscious choices, worthy of the deepest appreciation. Sometimes they strengthen my connection with the scenes, with the characters, and even with the film as a whole. The seventh art seems to have this anthropophagic ability to absorb its predecessors in its own way, creating unforgettable combinations.</p>
<p>
I dedicate this playlist and list of films to Cinearte Palace, the last street cinema in Juiz de Fora that, tragically, ended its activities in 2017. A more than special place, of cultural and cinematographic resistance to the commercial doldrums, where I experienced many of the memories here shared.</p>
<p>

<div style="margin: 25px 0px">

<iframe src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/playlist/7p8v5VBR4dmB66zukdRnNr"
    width="100%"
    height="480"
    frameborder="0"
    allowtransparency="true"
    allow="encrypted-media"></iframe>

</div>
</p>
<ol>
<li>Jules et Jim (1962), François Truffaut</li>
<li>Hable con ella (2002), Pedro Almodóvar</li>
<li>Cidade de Deus (2002), Fernando Meirelles &amp; Kátia Lund</li>
<li>The Dreamers (2003), Bernardo Bertolucci</li>
<li>Que Horas Ela Volta? (2015), Anna Muylaert</li>
<li>Volver (2006), Pedro Almodóvar</li>
<li>Deus e o Diabo na Terra do Sol (1964), Glauber Rocha</li>
<li>Boi Neon (2015), Gabriel Mascaro</li>
<li>Une robe d&#39;été (1996), François Ozon</li>
<li>Hotel Chevalier (2007), Wes Anderson</li>
<li>Moonrise Kingdom (2012), Wes Anderson</li>
<li>Cazuza: O Tempo Não Pára (2004), Walter Carvalho &amp; Sandra Werneck</li>
<li>Buena Vista Social Club (1999), Wim Wenders</li>
<li>Orfeu Negro (1959), Marcel Camus</li>
<li>Ma vie en rose (1997), Alain Berliner</li>
<li>Jack et la mécanique du coeur (2013), Stéphane Berla &amp; Mathias Malzieu</li>
<li>Scent of a Woman (1992), Martin Brest</li>
<li>The Forbidden Dance (1990), Greydon Clark</li>
<li>Beetlejuice (1988), Tim Burton</li>
<li>Pulp Fiction (1994), Quentin Tarantino</li>
<li>Reservoir Dogs (1992), Quentin Tarantino</li>
<li>Across the Universe (2007), Julie Taymor</li>
<li>Reservoir Dogs (1992), Quentin Tarantino</li>
<li>Velvet Goldmine (1998), Todd Haynes</li>
<li>Reservoir Dogs (1992), Quentin Tarantino</li>
<li>Kôkaku Kidôtai (1995), Mamoru Oshii</li>
<li>Trainspotting (1996), Danny Boyle</li>
<li>B-Movie: Lust &amp; Sound in West-Berlin 1979-1989 (2015), Jörg A. Hoppe &amp; Heiko Lange</li>
<li>T2 Trainspotting (2017), Danny Boyle</li>
<li>Manhattan (1979), Woody Allen</li>
<li>Dirty Dancing (1987), Emile Ardolino</li>
<li>Footloose (1984), Herbert Ross</li>
<li>American Psycho (2000), Mary Harron</li>
<li>The Crow (1994), Alex Proyas</li>
<li>Moonlight (2016), Barry Jenkins</li>
<li>Blue Velvet (1986), David Lynch</li>
<li>Blue Velvet (1986), David Lynch</li>
<li>Walk the Line (2005), James Mangold</li>
<li>2001: A Space Odyssey (1968), Stanley Kubrick</li>
<li>Interview with the Vampire (1994), Neil Jordan</li>
<li>Le jeune Karl Marx (2017), Raoul Peck</li>
<li>Moulin Rouge! (2001), Baz Luhrmann</li>
<li>Baby Driver (2017), Edgar Wright</li>
<li>Fight Club (1999), David Fincher</li>
<li>Donnie Darko (2001), Richard Kelly</li>
<li>The Lost Boys (1987), Joel Schumacher</li>
<li>Dark Shadows (2012), Tim Burton</li>
<li>Zodiac (2007), David Fincher</li>
<li>500 Days of Summer (2009), Marc Webb</li>
<li>The Doors: When You&#39;re Strange (2009), Tom DiCillo</li>
<li>20,000 Days on Earth (2014), Iain Forsyth &amp; Jane Pollard</li>
<li>Trainspotting (1996), Danny Boyle</li>
<li>Her (2013), Spike Jonze</li>
<li>La La Land (2016), Damien Chazelle</li>
<li>Billy Elliot (2000), Stephen Daldry</li>
<li>Into the Wild (2007), Sean Penn</li>
<li>Captain Fantastic (2016), Matt Ross</li>
<li>Dancer in the Dark (2000), Lars von Trier</li>
<li>Léon (1994), Luc Besson</li>
<li>Låt den rätte komma in (2008), Tomas Alfredson</li>
<li>Whiplash (2014), Damien Chazelle</li>
<li>Lilja 4-ever (2002), Lukas Moodysson</li>
<li>The Silence of the Lambs (1991), Jonathan Demme</li>
<li>Boyhood (2014), Richard Linklater</li>
<li>Aquarius (2016), Kleber Mendonça Filho</li>
<li>Sonnenallee (1999), Leander Haußmann</li>
<li>Beetlejuice (1988), Tim Burton</li>
<li>Apocalypse Now (1979), Francis Ford Coppola</li>
<li>The Wicker Man (1973), Robin Hardy</li>
<li>A Clockwork Orange (1971), Stanley Kubrick</li>
<li>Blade Runner (1982), Ridley Scott</li>
<li>Apocalypse Now (1979), Francis Ford Coppola</li>
<li>Blade Runner (1982), Ridley Scott</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
